We can think of our markup for this particular document as having five phases. We begin with preparatory cleanup (Phase 1), after which we tag major structural components (Phase 2, blocks but not inline snippets). At that point we do a bit of manual cleanup (Interlude, Phase 3) and add a root element to create a well-formed document. We next tag italics (Phase 4) and, finally, clean up blank lines (Phase 5). Your solution does not have to be divided into phases and does not have to follow our order.

Phase 1: Preparation

Reserved characters

We search for ampersands, less-than signs, and greater-than signs in the original text, since if they were there we would have to replace them with character entities to keep them from looking like markup characters. There aren’t any, but we can’t know that without looking for them, so this is always the first thing we do with any up-conversion task.

Remove extraneous newlines

Match: \n{3,}

Replace with: \n\n

Dot matches all status: Unchecked (doesn’t matter, since there is no dot in the match pattern)

Discussion: We trim instances of multiple blank lines down to a single blank line. For example, initially there are four blank lines between the title of the novel, on the first line, and the label CHAPTER I, on the sixth. Our match pattern uses numerical quantification to match sequences of three or more newlines, but because numerical quantification works only in match patterns, and not in replacements, we have to write two literal newlines into the replacement. There are several alternatives ways to match two or more sequential newlines, so you’re welcome to use whatever you prefer. You don’t have to remove extra newlines at all, but we find that doing so makes the document easier to work with.

Phase 2: Structural markup

Tag paragraphs

Match: \n\n

Replace with:

\n\n

Dot matches all status: Unchecked (doesn’t matter, since there is no dot in the match pattern)

Discussion: We use a blank line (two consecutive newlines) as a surrogate for the transition from one paragraph to the next, so we replace the two newlines with two newlines that have a paragraph end-tag before them and a paragraph start-tag after them. We then fix the first and last paragraphs manually since we’re matching transitions between paragraphs, and the first has no preceding paragraph and the last has no following paragraph. When we’re done with this step our document is a sequence of <p> elements with blank lines between them, and although it is well-balanced, it is not well-formed because it has no root element.

This method erroneously tags some non-paragraphs as paragraphs, most conspicuously the novel title and chapter labels (e.g., CHAPTER I) titles (e.g., JONATHAN HARKER'S JOURNAL, subtitles (e.g., (_Kept in shorthand._)). We find it simplest to let our pattern overgeneralize and then retag these items than to try to exclude them from the initial match pattern.

It is possible to match and replace the paragraphs themselves, rather than the blank lines between them, by using regex lookaround. This is more elegant than the approach we describe above because it does not require manual fix-up, but we nonetheless match the blank lines between paragraphs because we find that easier to understand.

Tag chapter headings

Match:

(CHAPTER.+)

Replace with: \1

Dot matches all status: Must be unchecked.

Discussion: We tag the chapter headings before the titles, subtitles, or the chapters as a whole because they are the easiest to match. Once we’ve tagged them distinctively, we can use our introduced <heading> tags to help find chapter beginnings. It’s fine if you chose to omit the heading as a separate element and instead used an attribute on your chapter tags, e.g., <chapter n="I">.

We’ve assumed that chapter headings, titles, and subtitles all occupy only a single line. A novel with very long chapter titles or subtitles might include newlines in these elements, and our pattern would fail to match in those cases. Whether you make the simplifying assumption that we do here or write a more robust pattern (which requires turning on Dot matches all and using non-greedy matching) is a matter of personal preference. In a short document where we can look at all the titles, such as here, we opt for the simpler pattern. If our corpus were so large that we couldn’t exclude the possibility of multi-line titles and we couldn’t realistically look at them all, we’d write the more robust regular expression.

Chapter titles

Match: (\n\n)

(.+)

Replace with: \1

\2

Dot matches all status: Must be unchecked

Discussion: The first pseudo-paragraph after the <heading> element is the chapter title, so we match the </heading> end-tag, the two newlines that follow it, and then the <p> element after the newlines, which represents the chapter title. We capture everything from that match except the <p> tags, which we replace with <title> tags. We used the element name <title> instead of something like <chapter-title> because we’re going to tag the chapters, so we’ll be able to distinguish titles of chapters from the title of the novel (which we’ll also tag as <title>) by the context.

Chapter subtitles

Match: (

\n\n)

(\(_.+_\))

Replace with: \1

\2

Dot matches all status: Must be unchecked

Discussion: The first chapter has what we consider a subtitle and the second one doesn’t. To distinguish them we hypothesize that if a chapter title is followed by a 1) one-line paragraph that is 2) bracketed by parentheses and 3) italicized (represented by underscores inside the parentheses) it represents a subtitle. If the paragraph that follows the title is longer than one line or lacks the parentheses or lacks the italics, we assume that it’s a regular chapter paragraph, and not a subtitle.

Chapters

Match:

Replace with: \n\n\n\n\0

Dot matches all status: Unchecked (doesn’t matter, since there is no dot in the match pattern)

Discussion: After running the find-and-replace we have to remove manually the spurious end-tag before the first chapter and we have to add the missing end-tag after the last chapter.

Chapters are tesselated, which means that each one starts where the last one ends, as was also the case with paragraphs. We can use that information to find the start position of the chapters by using the elements that we introduced and assuming that the start of any chapter marks the end of the preceding one. As with paragraphs, that assumption will fail for the first and last chapters because the first doesn’t follow any chapter, so we’ll have inserted a spurious end-tag that we’ll then need to remove, and the second doesn’t have a following chapter, so we’ll incorrectly have failed to insert its end-tag, which we’ll have to add manually. With only two chapters, both of which require manual fix-up, it would be reasonable to tag them both manually, but if we were tagging the entire novel the amount of correct tagging would be much greater than the two extremes that we need to adjust, so the regex-supported approach, even with the clean-up it requires, would simplify the job.

We sometimes refer to the approach that we adopt for our tesselated chapters and paragraphs as a milestone method. Milestones are single numbered mile markers on the highway (nowadays metal signs, but once upon a time stone pillars) that record simultaneous, with one statement, the beginning of a new mile (or mile segment) and the end of the preceding one. Similarly we assume that the transitions between paragraphs or between chapters are milestones that mark, at the same time, the end of the preceding element and the beginning of the new one.

Because milestones signify transitions, the very beginning and very end require special treatment, since the start of the first paragraph can’t also mark the end of the preceding paragraph because there isn’t one, etc. The milestone method isn’t the only way to tag tesselated structures (see our treatment of dated diary entries, below), but where we find it easier to think of finding the transition between items than of finding the items themselves, we have to remember that the first and last items will typically require manual fix-up.

Dated diary entries: start-tags

Match:

_(\d.+)_--

Replace with: \n\n\1\n\n

Dot matches all status: Must be unchecked

Discussion: Diary entries consist of multiple paragraphs. The first paragraph of an entry begins with a date and place surrounded by underscores (which represent italics) and followed by two hyphens. That brief date and place are not the entry (they are just the heading for an entry), and neither is the single paragraph that begins with the date and place (that is just the first paragraph of a multi-paragraph entry). Because the dated diary entry consists of multiple paragraphs, we need to wrap our diary-entry tags around all of them.

To enter the start-tag for all diary entries we extract the entry heading from the paragraph where it occurs, which must be the first paragraph of a diary entry. We tag the extracted date and place as a <date-place>, and add a start-tag for a <dated-entry> before it (not forgetting to restore the paragraph start-tag, which now comes after the new <date-place> element). We remove the double hyphen since it was present only to separate the date and place from the actual entry, and now that distinguish it with markup, we no longer need the pseudo-markup characters. We add the end-tags for diary entries in a separate step. We’ve chosen kebab case (hyphenation) for this element name for a reason, about which we’ll say more below. We make the same simplifying assumption about length here as with chapter headings, title, and subtitles, that is, we assume that all of these diary entry date and place records do not cross a newline.

Dates and places (optional)

Tagging the date and place reference at the beginning of a dated entry as just a single element is fine, but in Real Life we would tag the date and the (optional) place inside, as well. Because only two of the six entries contain a place after the date, and the rest contain only the date, we find it easier to tag the dates and places separately:

Dates

Match: (.+?\.)(.*)

Replace with:

\1

\2

Dot matches all status: Must be unchecked

Discussion: The date part of a <date-place> element will always be present, and consists of the content up to and including the first dot character. We match and wrap that in <date> tags. There may or may not be text, representing the place, after the date portion, and for now we just capture it and write it back as is, without markup.

Places

Match:

(.+?)

Replace with:

\1

Dot matches all status: Must be unchecked

Discussion: If there are any characters between the </date> end-tag that we created in the last step and the </date-place> end-tag, those must be the place, which we capture and wrap in <place> tags. If there is no text in that position, the match fails.

Dated diary entries: end-tags at the ends of chapters

Match:

Replace with: \n\n\0

Dot matches all status: Unchecked (doesn’t matter, since there is no dot in the match pattern)

Discussion:

The end of a diary entry is marked in one of two ways. If the diary entry is at the end of the chapter (two occurrences, since we have two chapters) there is no special mark, and the end of the chapter implicitly ends the diary entry, and we’ll add those end-tags here first. We discuss the second type in the next step.

There are, then, two related aspects to tagging diary entries: 1) wrap the diary-entry tags around all of the paragraphs that together constitute the diary entry and 2) tag the label distinctively. We chose to remove the label from the first paragraph and treat it as a structural component of the entry that precedes all of the paragraphs, that is, that is not contained within the first paragraph (even though it is rendered that way in the plain text).

Dated diary entries: end-tags not at the end of chapters

Match: (

\n\n)()

Replace with: \1\n\n\2

Dot matches all status: Unchecked (doesn’t matter, since there is no dot in the match pattern)

Discussion: If the diary entry is preceded within the same chapter by another diary entry, it is preceded by a paragraph (four occurrences). On three of those four occurrences the preceding paragraph is a single line that contains only asterisks and space characters, but we don’t need to care about that because any paragraph that immediately precedes the beginning of a new diary entry is necessarily the last paragraph of the preceding entry.

Asterisks

Match:

[* ]+

\n\n

Replace with: [nothing]

Dot matches all status: Unchecked (doesn’t matter, since there is no dot in the match pattern)

Discussion: The pseudo-paragraphs that contain just asterisks and space characters are pseudo-markup that signals a separation of dated diary entries (although not consistently). Now that we have tagged the diary entries these lines carry no information that we need, so we delete them.

Phase 3: Interlude

By this point we have tagged all of the major structural components of the text except the novel title at the top, and we also do not yet have a root element. We fix that by changing the element name for the title at the top (currently

DRACULA

) to

manually, and also by adding a root element around the entire content.

At this point our document is well-formed XML. If you have been working inside a document that you created as a new XML document, <oXygen/> knows that it’s XML and should show you a happy green square. If you created a plain text document to work in, at this point you need to save it as XML (File → Save as and give it a filename that ends in .xml) and then close and reopen it. Just saving it as XML isn’t enough for <oXygen/> to recognize that it is now an XML document that can be checked for well-formedness; you need to close and reopen it.

Once you’re looking at a well-formed XML document you should pretty-print it to improve the legibility. None of the steps below should interfere with well-formedness, so your document should remain well formed for the rest of the processing.

Phase 4: Italics

A regular-expression search for _.+?_ with Dot matches all checked reveals that there are eight instances of italics in this document, represented by underscores that surround small amounts of content. These instances have three different types of meaning: two are in a foreign language (boyar, Quatre Face), four are memorandum notations (Mem.), and two are parts of titles or subtitles and are italicized for no clear reason. Quatre Face has a newline between the two words, and we would fail to find it if we were to search for the simpler pattern _.+_ with Dot matches all unchecked. That is, we can’t safely assume, as we did with other structures earlier, that no italicized phrase will cross a newline boundary.

We can’t use regular expressions to find foreign words, which we’d like to tag as , but we can find the other two types with regular expressions, tag them as simply (presentational, because we cannot impute a meaning to the italics in these cases), and then tag whatever is left as .

Remember when we said that we used the element name <dated-entry> (kebab case, with a hyphen) for a reason? We could safely have used camel case (<datedEntry>), but the point is that we wanted to avoid snake case (<dated_entry>) because introducing underscores would have complicated searching for italics, which were represented in the original input document by underscores. We could have worked around the issue because the <oXygen/> find-and-replace dialog would let us exclude characters in element names from our search (check the Enable XML search options at the bottom of the dialog to see the interface), but since we didn’t have to create markup that would require us to fine-tune our search for italics in that way, we decided that it was simplest just to avoid introducing our own new underscores.

Memoranda

Match: _Mem\._

Replace with: Mem.

Dot matches all status: Unchecked (doesn’t matter, since there is no dot in the match pattern except the literal, escaped one)

Discussion: We escape the dot in the match pattern because we want to match a literal dot, and without the backslash that part of the pattern would match any character except a newline. In practice it doesn’t matter because we know that the document contains no four-letter italic words with the shape MenX, where X stands for any character except a newline, except when X is a literal dot. It’s nonetheless useful to get in the habit of distinguishing literal dots from the dot that is a metacharacter.

Titles and subtitles

Match: <(title|subtitle)>(.*?)_(.+?)_(.*?)

Replace with: <\1>\2\3\4

Dot matches all status: Must be unchecked

Discussion: We know that the title and subtitle that contain italics don’t include any newline characters, so we uncheck Dot matches all to ensure that that we don’t accidentally overrun the end of a line. We chose to match the title and the subtitle with the same regex, but there’s nothing wrong with using separate expressions if you find that easier to work with. Our regular expression as the following parts, in order:

A left angle bracket, which begins a start-tag for a title or subtitle.

An or-group of two strings, matching either of the start-tags we care about, but not any other start-tags. We wrap the or-group in parentheses to capture whatever we match, which means that when we match a

element the value of the first capture group (\1) will be equal to the string title, and when we match a subtitle it will be equal to subtitle.

A right angle bracket, closing the start-tag. Matching tags with regular expressions is a fragile process because the start-tag could legally have any amount of whitespace (spaces, newlines, tabs) before the closing angle bracket and it could also contain attributes. We know that isn’t the case in this document, though. The take-away is that processing arbitrary XML with regular expressions is not realistic, but processing limited, specific XML that you know well (in this case because you created yourself it) may be useful.

Zero or more characters up to the first underscore encountered. We capture this as the part of the title or subtitle that precedes any italics, and we wrap it in parentheses, so that it becomes the value of our second capture group.

An underscore, which marks the beginning of the italic portion. We don’t capture the underscore because we’re going to replace it with real markup.

Everything after the first underscore up to the second one, which becomes the third capture group.

Everything after the second underscore until the end of the line. This will include any non-italicized text that might follow the italics, as well as the end-tag.

Notes: Our pattern will fail to tag any italic phrase inside a title or subtitle except the first one, but since we know that there can be at most one in this document, that isn’t an issue. Any title or subtitle that doesn’t contain any underscores won’t match the pattern, so it will be ignored.

Foreign words

Match: _(.+?)_

Replace with: \1

Dot matches all status: Must be checked in case foreign phrases span newlines, and that happens in our document with Quatre Face.

Discussion: The only remaining paired underscores are around the two foreign expressions, so we can run a relatively simple search for text between underscores, capture it, and replace it with itself, throwing away the underscores and wrapping it in tags instead.

Phase 5: Blank lines

The blank lines served a structural purpose in the original plain-text source and we used them to control some of our tagging, but now that our document is fully tagged we no longer need them. You can leave them if you find the XML more legible with them, but if you want to delete them, you can search for two consecutive newlines (\n\n\ and replace them with a single newline.

Optional, extra-credit schema

The following schema matches the markup we’ve added to the document:

# Schema for first two chapters of Dracula
# 
start = novel
# 
# Mixed content that appears in multiple places
content = mixed { (italic | foreign)* }
# 
# Main hierarchy is novel -> chapter -> dated-entry -> p
novel = element novel { title, chapter+ }
chapter = element chapter { heading, title, subtitle?, dated-entry+ }
dated-entry = element dated-entry { date, p+ }
p = element p { content }
# 
# Titles and subtitles may have mixed content, like paragraphs
title = element title { content }
subtitle = element subtitle { content }
#
# Dates, italic, foreign, and heading elements have text content
date = element date { text }
italic = element italic { text }
foreign = element foreign { text }
heading = element heading { text }

We’ve generalized a bit and assumed that elements that can contain italics or foreign phrases might (in other chapters) contain any combination of those two element types. For that reason we define a named pattern with the label content so that we can reuse it in multiple places without having to retype it. In that way, should we decide to add another inline element we could add it to the schema in one place and it would be available wherever we’ve used the pattern.

Computational Methods in the Humanities

Projects

Fall 2024

Constitutional Thinkers
Representation in Shakespeare: Language and Appearances

Spring 2024

Constitutions of the Former Soviet Union
Sevdah: An etymological study of Bosnian song and poetry
Women in Folklore

Projects from Past Semesters

Projects Hosted on Obdurodon (Pitt Oakland)
Projects Hosted on Newtfire

Project Guildelines

Early in the semester groups of students will identify, though consultation with the instructors, a public domain text (that is, without copyright restrictions) in the humanities that interests them and a set of related research questions, and will work with that text throughout the semester, performing document analysis, developing and implementing a formal structural model, encoding (marking up) the text according to that model, developing programs to perform research with that text, and constructing a web site to publish their research. Each project team will meet weekly for approximately one hour with a project mentor (one of the instructors) outside class for project planning and discussion. This chart provides a rough idea of weekly progress over the course of the semester.

We will manage course projects in an online professional development environment called GitHub, and we’ll explain how it works and what the relevant terms (repo, issue, project, etc.) mean in class, so if you’re reading this at the beginning of the semester, don’t worry about the jargon or the technical details.

Once project teams have been formed, each team will post a weekly project update, in the form of an Issue on the designated TopHat discussion forum, due each Friday. (These weekly postings are per team, not per student, though every team member should be responsible for writing and posting at least once throughout the semester.) These postings should be status reports about your projects and should address four topics: 1) what you accomplished in the preceding week, 2) what you learned, 3) where you got stuck (and how you plan to get unstuck), and 4) what you plan to accomplish in the upcoming week. Reports are typically brief, but they should address both the state of the project in general and the specific weekly contributions of each of the individual team members. The instructors will show you how to use the Projects and Issues tabs in your GitHub repos (which is what we do in our own research) to manage tasks, timeliness, and any impediments you might face. Weekly project update postings should refer (with links) to specific new or revised content on the repo.

Unlike with projects in many other courses, the project evaluation is based not only on the final product, but also on regular, steady progress on individual project related tasks, and your instructors will work with you to identify appropriate weekly goals for your project using Github Projects. Weekly progress will be graded on the following scale: exceeds target (A+), meets target (A), some progress (B), minimal progress (C), no progress (F); the lowest two Project Progress grades will be excluded from the course grade. Because the primary purpose of the project is for students to learn how to use the Digital Humanities tools and methods employed by professionals, the instructors will work with you during your weekly project meetings to help you learn to apply the necessary methods to your own research, and obtaining your results according to those methods is part of the evaluation of the project. If your team determines your research needs a technology or method not taught in depth in the course, please speak with an instructor, who will help you figure out how to incorporate it. All project components (weekly progress = 30%, midterm task = 10%, final result = 20%), taken together, are worth 60% of the course grade.

Before you begin

There’s a lot that we could do to autotag this document and it isn’t realistic to try to squeeze all of it into a homework assignment, so we’ll stop at some point and leave the rest as optional bonus tasks.

The text

Oscar Wilde’s

The importance of being Earnest

is available in plain text from Project Gutenberg at http://www.gutenberg.org/cache/epub/844/pg844.txt. Download the text and manually remove the Project Gutenberg boilerplate from the beginning and end, so that all that remains is the text as Oscar Wilde wrote it.

The task

Your task is to begin to prepare an XML-encoded digital edition of this play from the plain text using search and replace operations to introduce the markup. As is appropriate for a play, we eventually want the XML to identify any of the following that it finds: acts, scenes, settings, speeches, speakers, and stage directions. Our goal is to use search and replace operations with regular expressions to create descriptive well-formed XML markup (rather than, for example, to create a presentational HTML editon). We want to avoid manual tagging except in situations that occur so rarely that they don’t justify search and replace operations, such as tagging the title of the play or creating a root element.

What to submit

For this homework assignment please complete just the tasks described below and submit a markdown document describing the steps you took. Include your exact regular expressions and, if you are matching and replacing something, the exact replacement expression. For each regex operation, specify whether dot-matches-all was checked or unchecked. Note that we are not asking you to tag speeches or speakers yet, even though that’s most of the text; those are optional bonus tasks.

Steps to complete

Delete the Gutenberg boilerplate manually.

Use regex to search for and replace reserved characters. What are they, and how many did you find?

Use regex to collapse multiple blank lines, leaving only one blank line betweeen lines of the input document.

Use regex to remove multiple consecutive space characters to leave only single spaces.

Manually select and cut everything before the line that says FIRST ACT and save it to a different file. In Real Life you would tag that separately later and then paste it back in.

Italics are represented by underscores. There are seven instances, which seem to fall into three types:

Emphasis, e.g., I believe it _is_ a very pleasant state, sir.

Newspaper title, e.g., … will appear in the _Morning Post_ on Saturday …

Individual punctuation marks that seem to have been italicized for no apparent reason, e.g., [Lane goes out_._]

Use regex to:

Strip out the underscores around the single punctuation marks without replacement.

Assume that if the content begins with an upper-case letter it represents a newspaper title and use regex to replace the underscores with <title> tags.

Assume that the rest are emphasis and replace the underscores with <emph> tags.

Stage directions (that is, actions performed by characters) are inside square brackets, sometimes on their own line and sometimes inside a speech. A speech may have more than one stage direction, and stage directions may cross line boundaries. Nothing else is inside square brackets. Use regex to tag all stage directions as <stage>, removing the square brackets.

As a way of learning about how acts and scenes are labeled, search for every line that contains no lower-case letters with ^[^a-z\n]+$. (This is a negated character class; see the discussion at https://www.regular-expressions.info/charclass.html.) Note that acts begin with the act number, then SCENE, and then they end with ACT DROP, except that the last one ends with TABLEAU. Since every act has just one scene, use a regex to remove the lines that say SCENE or ACT DROP or TABLEAU (including their trailing new lines) by replacing them with nothing. You can do this with a single regex.

Now tag all of the act labels (lines that read FIRST ACT, etc.) as <act> elements. These aren’t really acts; they’re just the headings for acts, and in Real Life we would then use those labels to tag the actual acts.

There appears to be a description of the setting, in the form of a plain-text paragraph, at the beginning of each act, we can find it because it occurs immediately after the "ACT" label, and those are the only places where the string "ACT", all in upper case, occurs. Find these paragraphs using regex and tag them as <setting>.

Optional bonus activities

The bulk of this document is speeches, which are separated from one another by blank lines. You want to tag each speech, and each speaker at the beginning of each speech, along the lines of:

  Algernon
  No cucumbers!

You don’t have to tag lines because the speeches in this play are prose, so the lineation is not informational. Be careful, though! Some speaker names might include dots, some speeches might be spoken by more than one person in unison, some speeches might include stage directions in places where you don’t expect them, and not everything between blank lines is a speech.

Computational Methods in the Humanities

Standing Assignments

In addition to coding assignments; response papers; and unit tests; the following "standing assignments" are due on a continuous / weekly / monthly basis.

Discussion Forum and Troubleshooting Post (Slack)

Despite the image of the programmer as a solitary soul bent over a glowing screen in a cubicle, programming is, in reality, a social activity, and real programmers make liberal use of discussion forums to ask and answer questions. Furthermore, despite the classroom tradition where students submit homework to a professor, who grades and returns it, so that nobody else ever sees it, that’s not the way coding works in the real world and it’s not the model in this course. Like real developers, we ask and answer questions in the open. This course component has two principal goals: 1) it provides a forum to ask and answer questions, and 2) it helps course participants become familiar with an industry-standard discussion platform.

Each student is required to read all new discussion postings on the relevant Slack channel; consistently respond to other student's post; and regularly post original submissions: ask a question, answer a question (comment on an existing posting, typically in a thread), make a suggestion, pass along a link to a site that showed you something you could use in your project (and explain what it is and why it was useful), etc.

Participation in the discussion beyond the minimum requirement is strongly encouraged. Don’t be shy about asking questions in this forum; your instructors do this all the time in their own work, and you can’t learn to code if you don’t learn how to participate in a coding community. And don’t be shy about answering questions, which is both good citizenship and personally satisfying. Much of the classroom time will be devoted to teacher-centered instruction, and the discussion framework offers an opportunity to interact with classmates to cultivate a community in which peers provide insight, solutions, and general discussion. This discussion forum should be the first resource for questions, comments, etc.

Grading Rubric for Slack Posts

The criteria for this standing assignment may seem vague (what do we have in mind by "consistent" posting?) and there is no set quota in terms of frequency or length: students who actively use this forum as a learning tool will very likely receive full credit. Some students may do that by providing pointers and helpful links to other students' posts several times per week; others might write a multi-paragraph explainer on a new coding technique they figured out every other week; or something in between.

We will post a holistic grade in this category at least three times over the course of the semester. In determining that grade, will be considering the following factors:

Frequency: did the student post most weeks?
Detail: did the student clearly explain what they tried? Did they hypothesize what might have gone wrong?
Clarity: did the student illustrate what they attempted by providing their code using code blocks and /or linking to their Github file?
Collegiality: do at least some of the students' post respond to other students' queries, or otherwise illustrate that the student is engaging with other people's posts?
Promptness: did the student post a query or response with adequate time remaining before an assignment or project deadline?
Single Topics: how often has the student been engaging on the "single issue" prompts marked on the syllabus?

Being exceptionally strong in one of these areas can compensate for less attention to another.

Project Updates and Responses (Github)

Beginning the second week of the semester, each team should post frequent (usually weekly) updates about the status of their research project on their Github project repo, and each individual student is required to periodically (usually monthly) engage with updates posted by a different project team. These postings should be brief but informative status reports about your projects: what you accomplished in the preceding week, what you learned, where you got stuck, etc., as well was what you plan to do in the upcoming week. Reports must address both the state of the project in general and the specific weekly contributions of each of the individual team members.

Once the weekly project updates begin, each student is required to read all new Issue postings on the other project repos and periodically offer feedback and commentary. These responses may be brief, but they need to be thoughtful, something more than nice job! or very interesting! or I look forward to seeing what you do next! You might make a suggestion, offer a critique, ask (or answer) a question, discuss how something in someone else’s posting gives you an idea of something to do on your own project, share a link to a resource you discovered that might be useful for the other team, etc. You will find it helpful to follow the other teams’ repos, which you can do by clicking the Watch button at the top of their repo page. Issue responses are also assessed as check plus, check, and check minus.

Grading Rubric for Project Updates and Responses

As with the standing assignments, grades in this category will be holistic, and students will receive grades and feedback at least three times during the semester. Many of the criteria for grading are the similar to those of the standing assignments:

Frequency: did the team post updates most weeks?
Detail: did the updates provide information about concrete progress? Did the groups discuss intellectual questions related to the content of the research? Did they discuss coding issues, challenges, and goals?
Equity: is there evidence that all of the team members contributed equally?
Collegiality: have all team members also been engaging with other teams' project posts?
Promptness / consistency: Did the groups post updates relatively quickly after their team meetings, while still fresh in mind?
Single Topics: how often has the student been engaging on the "single issue" prompts marked on the syllabus?

Single Topic Prompts

On the syllabus you will periodically notice "single topics" described in the "Postings" column. These are not exactly "assignments" in the sense that you will not receive a separate grade for each of them. Rather, they are prompts for how to fulfill the standing assignments detailed above, which means you can respond to them either on the Slack channel or on Github. You do not need to respond to all of the single topics, but the frequency and quality of your engagement will count for or against your overall grade in the Standing Assignments category.

You can find an XML (TEI) version of Shakespeare’s

Hamlet

at http://dh.obdurodon.org/bad-hamlet.xml. We’ve deliberately damaged some of the markup in this edition to introduce some inconsistencies, but the file is well-formed XML, which means that you can use XPath to explore it. You should download this file to your computer (typically that means right-clicking on the link and selecting save as) and open it in <oXygen/>.

Prepare your answers to the following questions in a markdown file upload it to Canvas as an attachment. As always, code snippets (including XPath snippets) in markdown must be surrounded with backticks.

Some of these tasks are thought-provoking, and even difficult. If you get stuck, do the best you can, and if you can’t get a working answer, give the answers you tried and explain where they failed to get the results you wanted. As always, you are encouraged to ask questions in the #xpath channel in Slack, but because you want to make progress in learning to debug your own code, your questions should tell us what you tried, what you expected, exactly what you got instead (not just didn’t work or got an error), and what you think the source of the problem is. Sometimes writing that sort of request for advice that will help you figure out what’s wrong on your own (see Rubber duck debugging), and even when it doesn’t, it will help us identify the difficult moments.

These tasks require the use of path expressions, predicates, and functions. References to Kay are to the Michael Kay book; there’s a link in our online course description to a PDF version accessible through the Pitt library system. There may be more than one possible answer.

Using the

Bad Hamlet

document and the XPath browser window in <oXygen/>, construct XPath expressions that will do the following (give the full XPath expressions in your answers, and not just the results):

What XPath will return a hyphen-separated list of all characters without duplicates? The resulting list will look something like:

Claudius-Hamlet-Polonius ...

Our solution uses string-join() (alternative solutions may also require distinct-values()). Note that there are several ways to identify the characters in this markup, including the <castList> element, the <speaker> elements, and the @who atribute on the <sp> element. Which should you use and why?

The simplest solution is string-join(//role, '-') (or, with the arrow operator, //role => string-join('-') . This doesn’t use distinct-values(), since the values of <role> elements are already unique. In addition to uniqueness, it also separates characters who speak in unison. For example, if you use <speaker> elements you’ll find values like <speaker>Rosencrantz and Guildenstern</speaker>, and that isn’t a string you want in your list of characters. Furthermore, the <speaker> and @who values contain only speaking characters, so using those would miss non-speaking characters.

Most metrical lines (<l>) have an @xml:id attribute with a value like sha-ham101010, ending in a six-digit number. The first digit is the act, the next two the scene, and the last three the line in the scene. Some metrical lines are split across multiple speakers, and in that case the six-digit number in the @xml:id value is followed by I (initial part), M (middle part), or F (final part). In a few places there may be more than one middle part, and in those cases the M is followed by a one-digit number. For example, one of Hamlet’s lines is:

<l xml:id="sha-ham502277M2" n="277">One.</l>

which is the second middle part. What XPath will return the number of <l> elements that are middle parts? Our solution uses count() and contains().

//l[contains(@xml:id, 'M')] => count()

As we explained, any line that is a middle part will have the character M in its @xml:id. To test whether a line's attribute has this character, we use the contains() function inside a predicate. The contains() function checks whether its second argument exists within the first, that is, whether the capital M is anywhere in the value of @xml:id, which is a string.

To find all of these lines, we search on the descendant axis, starting from the document node, with the // shorthand, and append the predicate [contains(@xml:id, 'M')]. We then use the arrow operator with the count() function function to count them.

Sometimes Rosencrantz speaks by himself and sometimes he speaks in unison with Guildenstern. What XPath finds all of the speeches by Rosencrantz, whether alone or together with Guildenstern? Our solution uses a single instance of contains().

//sp[contains(@who, "Rosencrantz")]

This solution is very similar to the solution to the previous question, except that it uses the function contains() to search for the presence of an entire string instead of just a single character. It is important to know that contains() is capable of doing both. This XPath finds all of the <sp> elements and filters them by determining whether the string Rosencrantz occurs anywhere in the @who attribute, indicating that Rosencrantz is speaking. Where Rosencrantz and Guildenstern speak together, the @who value is instead Rosencrantz Guildenstern", but that also contains the string Rosencrantz.

The approach above will produce false positives if the play also has a character with a name like Rosencrantzenfeld because that also contains Rosencrantz as a substring. You can (= should) use the contains-token() function instead of contains()to avoid that peril.

The contains-token() function matches a substring only if it is a separate word, that is, not a substring of another word. In that way the contains-token() function is a compact and legible way of performing the same logic as //sp[tokenize(@who) = 'Rosencrantz']. This longer, less legible version uses the tokenize() function to split the value of the @who attribute into word tokens on whitespace (whitespace is the default separator for the tokenize() function if none is specified explicitly) and it then tests whether any of the tokens is equal to the string Rosencrantz.

The contains-token() function is new in XPath 3.0, so it is not included in Michael Kay’s book, which documents XPath and XSLT only through version 2.0.

The string-length() function can be used in two ways. You can wrap it around an argument, so that, for example, string-length('Hi, Mom!') will return 8, the length in character count of the string inside the quotation marks. It can also be used as part of a path expression, so that, for example, if the XPath //sp returns a sequence of all <sp> elements, //sp/string-length(.) returns a sequence of the lengths of all <sp> elements as measured by counting characters. This works by finding all of the <sp> elements and then (next path step) getting the string length of each one. Remember that the dot inside the parentheses refers to the current context node, which is the member of the sequence of <sp> nodes that is being processed at the moment. We need to use this subterfuge because string-length(//sp) generates an error. The problem is that string-length() can take only a single argument, and //sp returns more than one item. Putting the string-length() function on its own path step with a dot inside means that it applies once for every <sp> element, and that each time it applies, it has just a single argument.

Use this information to identify an XPath that finds the length of the longest speech. What length does it return? Our solution uses string-length() and max().

max(//sp/string-length(.))

We can read this from the inside out as first find all <sp> elements in the document; then, for each of them, count its length in characters; then, for the sequence of lengths (all of which are integers) return only the longest. Because we cannot find the string-length of more than one item at a time, we navigate to all of the <sp> elements in the play on the descendant axis with the // shorthand, and then take a step to use the string-length() function and use . to refer to the current <sp> for each one in turn. Wrapping the max() function around the XPath that produces this sequence of values will return the maximum value in that sequence, that is, the maximum length of any speech, which is 5248.

We find this much easier to read when we write it using the simple map and arrow operators:

//sp ! string-length(.) => max()

By the way, this is a naive and textually incorrect way to measure the length of a speech. It includes the content of any embedded <speaker> or <stage> elements, which aren’t part of the spoken text, and it also includes any whitespace characters that might have been present because of indentation during pretty-printing. How might you measure the length of a speech in a more textually meaningful way, and how would you do that using XPath?

Optional, challenging question: Given the preceding solution, how can you use that XPath to retrieve the longest <sp> itself? No fair checking the length and then writing a separate XPath that looks for that number. Your answer must find the longest speech without your knowing how long it is. Our solution doesn’t require any additional functions beyond the ones used in #4, but it does use a complicated predicate.

//sp[string-length(.) eq max(//sp ! string-length(.))]

Since the value returned by the previous solution is just a number, we can use it in a predicate to compare against the length of any speech that we are looking at. We first find the speeches and then check one by one whether the length of any of them is equal to the maximum length of all speeches in the play. This works because even within a predicate the // starts its search from the root of the document, so the comparison is to the maximal length of all speeches.

It is also possible to find the longest speech without building on #4. An expression that does that is: //sp[not(string-length(.) &lt; //sp/string-length(.))] This takes advantage of the fact that when we use the general comparison operator < (which we have to spell with the character entity &lt; because it’s inside an attribute value, where a literal < would not be well formed), the comparison returns true if any item on the left side of the operator is less than any item on the right (see the discussion of General comparison at the bottom of our XPath functions we use most). The right side of our comparison here is a sequence of integers that represent the lengths of all speeches, and the item on the left is the integer length of the speech we’re looking at at the moment (we look at each one separately, because that’s how predicates work). The only speech that is not shorter than at least one of the sequence of all speeches in the play is the one that is itself the longest, so our test will pick out just that one. As you gain more experience with using general comparison operators to compare sequences to one another this type of logic will grow more intuitive.

We don’t recommend the following alternative because it requires an extra statement, but it’s worthwhile knowing about the XPath let statement:

let $longest := max(//sp/string-length(.))
return //sp[string-length(.) eq $longest]

The let statement defines a variable, and in this case, we create a variable called $longest (variable names in XPath begin with a dollar sign) which we set equal to the value of the longest speech, which is the integer 5248. The binding operator, which binds the value of the the expression on its right to the variable name on its left, is a colon followed by an equal sign (:=), and not just an equal sign (as in some other programming languages). The binding operator is sometimes called the walrus operator because it looks like the eyes and tusks of a walrus lying on its side—at least if you have a lively imagination.

A let statement must be paired with a return statement, which normally uses the variable to compute the value of an XPath expression, so in this case the return statement returns a sequence of all <sp> elements with a string length equal to 5248. You can write the entire expression on one line if you prefer; we’ve broken it over two lines because we find it easier to read that way.

Optional, very challenging question: What XPath produces a numbered list of all characters, without any duplicates, which should look something like:

Claudius
Hamlet
Polonius
...

There are several possible solutions, each of which raises issues that you may not have seen before. If you get an error message, try to figure out what it means and how to resolve it.

One solution is //role ! concat(position(), ". " ,.). We retrieve all <role> elements and then, for each one, return a concatenation of its position in the sequence of <role> elements (using the position() function to get the position of the current context node in the sequence selected by the preceding path step), a literal dot followed by a space, and then the <role> element itself. The concat() function automatically atomizes its arguments, which is to say that when we pass it a <role> element, it converts it to its atomic (string) value (that is, it throws away the markup and just gives us back the character content), so that we wind up with results like “1. Claudius”, which is what we want.

There is, alternatively, a concatenation operator, spelled ||, that you can use instead of the concat() function. The expression with that operator would look like //role ! (position() || ". " || .).

If we get the characters using <speaker> or @who values instead of <role>, we need to deduplicate them with distinct-values(), and the the expression would be distinct-values(//speaker) ! concat(position(), ". " ,.).

Finally, instead of iterating over the roles or distinct <speaker> or @who values and returning their positions and string values, as we do above, we can iterate over the positions and return the same thing. The expression in that case would be

for $i in (1 to count(//role)) 
return concat($i, ". ", (//role)[$i])

The for expression iterates over a sequence and does something once for each member of the sequence. The sequence over which it iterates is a sequence of integers from 1 through however many characters there are in the play (there are 37, which XPath determines by counting the number of <role> elements). We use the to operator, which we haven’t used before, as an instruction to generate the sequence of integers for us dynamically. If there were, say, only 5 characters in the play, the expression 1 to count(//role) would be equivalent to the sequence (1,2,3,4,5).

Although for $i in (1 to count(//role)) is just setting the variable $i to a different integer value each time it loops, on each pass through the for loop (//role)[$i] will point to a different character in the play. On the first pass, when $i equals 1, (//role)[$i] means (//role)[1], so it points to the first character in the sequence returned by //role. On the second pass, the number value is 2 and (//role)[$i] means (//role)[2], and points to the second character. This is what lets us generate our numbered list; both the numbers and the pointers into the list of characters are incremented by one on each pass through the loop. You can read more about how this works in http://xsltbyexample.blogspot.com/2010/05/obtain-position-from-for-expression-in.html, which details specifically how and why you would use this approach. We find this the least intuitive of the options discussed here, so it isn’t the one we’d choose in Real Life. It’s nonetheless worth knowing how for expressions work, but because simple map and path expressions have an implicit for built into every step (since the step to the right of the slash or bang is applied once for each item in the sequence to the left), we use explicit for statements much less in XPath than we do in many other programming languages.

In many instances we can apply an operation to a sequence of nodes with either a slash or simple mapping. For example, the following two expressions are equivalent, and each returns a sequence of integers that gives the string length for each act in the play, in document order (that is, from Act 1 through Act 5, consecutively):

//body/div ! string-length(.)
//body/div/string-length(.)

We recommend using the simple map operator where appropriate, such as in this situation, because it makes it easier to see when we are taking a path step and when we are applying a function to each member of a sequence.

There are, though, at least two important differences between the slash and the simple map operator in this context:

With both operations the sequence to the left supplies the input items, one by one, for the operation on the right. The slash requires that the sequence to the left be a sequence of nodes, while the simple map operator allows any sequence. For example:

The expression distinct-values(//speaker) ! string-length(.) will return the string length (number of letters) for each distinct speaker name.

The expression distinct-values(//speaker)/string-length(.) will raise an error because distinct values are strings, and not nodes.

Meanwhile, both //speaker ! string-length(.) and //speaker/string-length(.) will work because //speaker, unlike distinct-values(//speaker), is a sequence of nodes.

The slash sorts the items on the left into document order and removes duplicates before it passes them along to the operation on the right, which the bang does not do. The following example is a bit contrived (more natural examples occur inside XSLT transformations, but not in stand-alone XPath expressions):

The expression

(
  //body/div => 
  sort((),function($i) {string-length($i)})
)
! head

sorts the acts from shortest to longest by string-length and returns the act labels. The results are, in order, the <head> children of acts 4, 2, 5, 1, 3. That is, Act 4 is the shortest act and Act 3 is the longest with respect to string length.

You can read about the sort() function at https://www.w3.org/TR/xpath-functions-31/#func-sort.

If we replace the simple map operator in the XPath expression above with the slash we re-sort the results into document order, so that the results are, in order, acts 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. This is probably not what we want or we wouldn’t have sorted them in the first place.

Skip to main content

Digital Methods in Humanistic Research

Course Description

This is a course about using computational methods to unlock new insights in humanistic research: how can coding help you see things in a (historical, literary, philosophical, linguistic) text that might otherwise be invisible? By the end of one semester, students with no prior coding experience (our target constituency) will be seasoned researchers in the digital humanities.

"Digital humanities" is a capacious rubric, and "coding" does not narrow it down much either. Humanists tend to be especially interested in texts, and so this course focuse on coding languages (especially XML and related methods) that allow the computer to better understand a text and endow it with new meanings.

Even though students will spend a lot of their time coding, this is a humanities research course before it is a coding course: the computer is the means, not the ends. It is therefore fitting that the centerpiece of this course is a research project, the topic of which is entirely driven by student interests, and to which students will begin applying their newly-learned coding skills immediately.

Legacy

This course is modeled very closely on one pioneered by emeritus Pitt Professor David Birnbaum, and we will be using much of the material available on his website: Obdurodon. (What is an "Obdurodon," you ask? An extinct platypus with molars, apparently... don't worry about it.) For our purposes, Obdurodon functions as an encylcopedia of information essential for this course, and many of the links to coding assignments on the syllabus redirect there as well. Just bear in mind that specific course information on Obdurodon (e.g., due dates, classroom assignments) may relate to a previous semester. For a more detailed description of assignments and policies, follow this link.

Dr. Birnbaum summed up the impetus for this course as follows:

"Humanities students often do not realize (or even imagine) that 1) they are capable of learning to write useful and practical computer programs within the course of a semester even if they have no prior background in programming; 2) the ability to write one's own programs can be valuable for scholars in the humanities, especially because commercial software often does not address research needs in the humanities; and 3) practical computer programming, no less than reading, writing, and arithmetic, is a useful skill that is within the reach of any educated person regardless of academic specialization."